Guide to the Duke Chapel Carillon Records, 1929-2022, undated UA.17.01.0008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Chapel Carillon Records
1924-2022
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hammond, J. Samuel
UA.17.01.0008
14.5 Linear Feet
The Duke Chapel fifty-bell carillon was installed in 1932 and is used to play afternoon recitals, and programs on holidays and other public occasions. Duke's carillon has been played by university carillonneurs Anton Brees and J. Samuel Hammond. The collection was created by Hammond, and contains records relating to the operations and activities of Duke Chapel carillon and ranges in date from 1929-2022. Materials include administrative records, correspondence, printed recital programs, carillon and carillonneur material, clippings, photographs, and performance recordings.
Arrangement
The Duke Chapel Carillon Records are arranged in the following Series: Objects; Administrative Records; Duke Chapel Carillon Restoration; Non-Duke Carillon Materials; Samuel Hammond Personal; and Carillon Recordings.
Collection Overview
The Duke Chapel Carillon Records were created by the university carillonneur J. Samuel Hammond, and contains records relating to the operations and activities of Duke Chapel carillon and ranges in date from 1929-2022. Materials include administrative records, correspondence, printed recital programs, carillon and carillonneur material, clippings, photographs, and performance recordings.
Biographical / Historical
The Duke Chapel Carillon Records contain the history of the Duke Chapel fifty-bell carillon which was installed in the tower in 1932 in honor of James B. Duke by George G. Allen and William Perkins, chairman and vice chairman of the Duke Endowment. It is used to play afternoon recitals, and programs on holidays and other public occasions. Duke's carillon is played manually from a keyboard located beneath the bells.
The instrument was cast in Loughborough, England by the John Taylor Bellfounders, Ltd. in 1932. The carillon was restored by the same company, now known as John Taylor and Co. in 1992. Anton Brees, who served as the first university carillonneur from 1932 to 1956, gave the inaugural recital on the Chapel carillon as part of commencement weekend in June 1932. While at Duke, Brees simultaneously played at the Bok Singing Tower at Lake Wales, Florida.
J. Samuel Hammond began playing the carillon in 1965 while a Duke undergraduate student in history. He became the Chapel Carillonneur in 1968. He later took on the position of music librarian, in 1974, making him the first music librarian at Duke. In 1986, Hammond transitioned to the role of rare book cataloger and was also designated university carillonneur by President Brodie. He retired from Duke University Libraries in 2012 and continued as university carillonneur until his retirement from the position in 2018. J. Samuel Hammond passed away in February 2021.
Related Materials
Chapel Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Duke Chapel Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Provenance
The Duke Chapel Carillon Records were received by the Duke University Archives as gifts from 2019-2022 and transfers in 2018 and 2022.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
carillon music; Carillonneurs; Duke Chapel (Durham, N.C.); Sheet music; Audio recordings.; Concerts -- North Carolina -- Durham; Scrapbooks -- North Carolina -- Durham; Administrative records; Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Administration; Hammond, Sam; Barnes, Ronald, 1927-1997; Johnson, Roy Hamlin; Brees, Anton
- Objects, 1930; 1992; undated
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access restricted. For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
  - Carillon coat finish sample, 1992 Sep 3 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes metal piece 'top coat' on one side.
  - Carillon paint samples, 1992 Apr 1; 2 items (Box 1)
    Includes two metal pieces; one labled Therabond ST200 primer; and one labled Alternative to gloss.
  - Carillon stain samples, 1992 Feb 11; 5 items (Box 1)
    Includes five wooden pieces with various stain samples for the clavier cabinet and batons.
  - Carillon downwire samples, 1992 Jan 23; 2 items (Box 1)
    Includes two metal downwire samples.
  - Carillon John Taylor nameplate, 1930 (Box 1)
    Includes the John Taylor & Co. Bell Founders & Carillon Builders nameplate from the 1930 keyboard.
  - Bell clapper, undated (Box 1)
  - Leather support, undated (Box 1)
- Administrative Records, 1924-2022; undated
  Includes policies, correspondence, and Duke-related documents.
  Access restricted. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
  - Julian Abele, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Anton Brees and George Allen, 1930-1935; undated (Box 4)
  - Duke Chapel Carillon History, 1939-2013 (Box 4)
  - Events Celebrating Duke Carillon, 1930-2015 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1930-2017; undated (Box 4)
  - Duke Chapel History, 1935-2007 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Memoranda, 1977-1998 (Box 4)
  - Student Papers, 1978-2013 (Box 4)
    FERPA information restricted until 2083.
  - Duke Marse Jack Bell, 1982-2004 (Box 4)
  - J. Benjamin Smith, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Herring Endowment, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Technical Services, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Rededication Ceremony, 1992 Oct 25 (Box 4)
  - Duke Boychoir, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Practice Keyboard Disposal Correspondence, 1993-2000 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1997; undated (Box 4)
  - GNCA Congresses, 1997-2004; undated (Box 4)
  - DU's Marshal Correspondence, 1997-2007 (Box 4)
  - Duke Recitals, 1997-2017 (Box 4)
  - Same Sex Unions, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Duke Chapel Elevator, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Roman Patrick, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Photographs, 2002-2004 (Box 4)
  - Hammond Payroll Change and Status Correspondence, 2012-2016 (Box 4)
  - Duke Chapel Keys, 2013 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Music Log, 2013-2015 (Box 4)
    Includes dates and music played on the Duke Carillon.
  - Carillon Music Log, 2016 January - 2018 December (Box 15)
  - Carillon Music Log, 2019 January - 2020 July (Box 15)
  - Carillon Music Log, 2020 August - 2022 August (Box 15)
  - Multiple Compositions, Damon Scott, 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    includes correspondence with Sam Hammond
  - Campanolgical Study No. 1, David Males, 1980 (Box 2)
    For Hammond, includes note.
  - Carillon Festival Poster, 1996 (Box 2)
    Poster features Hammond
  - Music Publication Correspondence, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Badinerie, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Benedicite Fanfaires, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Countess of Sussex Gazziarrl, Phillip Rosseler, undated (Box 2)
    Adapted by Sam Hammond.
  - Down to Georgia, Adger Williams, undated (Box 2)
  - Fluidity Jig, Adger Williams, undated (Box 2)
  - Introit, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - January Thaw, Adger Williams, undated (Box 2)
  - Kemp's Jig, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - The Lillac Tree, Adger Williams, undated (Box 2)
  - A Lullaby for Jon, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Polores et Pax, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Sarabande, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - The Sick Tune, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Spring Saunter, Adger Williams, undated (Box 2)
  - Three Poems of America, David Maves, undated (Box 2)
    For Sam Hammond, with note from the composer.
  - Untitled Composition, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Untitled Composition, Sam Hammond, undated (Box 2)
  - Untitled Composition, Unknown Composer, undated (Box 2)
- Duke Chapel Carillon Restoration, 1939-2018
  - Renovation and Restoration Articles and Memorabilia, 1939-2016 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Restoration Report, Richard Strauss, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Restoration Feasibility Study, Richard Strauss, original, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Carillon Restoration Feasibility Study, Richard Strauss, photocopy, 1988 May 2 (Box 3)
  - Carillon Renovation Fund, 1989-1993 (Box 4)
  - Chapel Carillon Inspection, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Taylor Contracts, Records, and Correspondence, 1990-1992; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Correspondence pertain to contracts and records
  - Restoration Memos, Committe Minutes, and Checks, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Painting, 1991-2005 (Box 4)
  - Carillon Photographs, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Carlton Bills, 2012-2013 (Box 4)
  - Restoration Correspondence, 1930-2018; undated; 8 folders (Box 4)
- Non-Duke Carillon Materials, 1955-2017
  Includes documentation of other carillons, carillonneurs, conferences, festivals, history, and recitals.
  - Walt Disney's Mouseketunes sheet music, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1997 (Box 5)
  - Roy Hamlin Johnson, 1969-2007 (Box 5)
  - First Presbyterian Church Carillon Concert, Gastonia, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Berkeley Carillon Festival, 1980-1998 (Box 5)
  - Bok Tower Carillon Festival, 1982-2004; 6 folders (Box 5)
  - John Powell Sheet Music, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Johan Franco, 1983-1987 (Box 5)
  - Sewanee Summer Carillon Series, Leonidas Polk Memorial Carillon, 1983-2016; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Richard Strauss, 1984-1998 (Box 5)
  - Summer Carillon Recitals, Belmont, 1984-2008 (Box 5)
  - Wake Forest University Carillon, Recital Series, Commencement, 1985-2005; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Covenant Presbyterian Church Carillon Recital, 1994-2006 (Box 5)
  - Cohast Carillon Recital, 1996; 2000; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Richmond World War I Memorial Carillon, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Tilton Memorial Carillon Festival, 1996; 2000; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Carillons, Charleston, 1997-2008 (Box 5)
  - Peter Paul Olejar Sheet Music, 1997-2018 (Box 5)
  - Springfield Park District Carillon Festival, 1998-2012; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - American Carillon Music Editions (ACME), Fiddle Tunes, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Carillon Recital for Gloucester, 2000 (Box 5)
  - John Knox, 2000 (Box 5)
  - James Lawson, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Carillon Conferences and Recitals, 2002-2017; undated (Box 5)
  - Hollins University Inauguration Service, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Joseph Dill Baker Carillon Recital, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Jill Johnston, Carillon History, 2009 (Box 5)
  - American Organist, 2016-05-01 (Box 5)
  - Holy Name of Jesus Cathedral, Raleigh, 2017 (Box 5)
- Samuel Hammond Personal, 1939-2021
  Includes correspondence, programs, articles, certificates, photographs, notes, and articles related to Hammond's retirement and his career as a carillonneur. Most of these materials maintain Hammond's original order and are otherwise arranged in chronological order. General correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by sender then chronologically.
  - Ronald Barnes Correspondence, 1976-1996 (Box 5)
    Hammond cites Ronald Barnes as a foremost American carillonneur, friend, and mentor.
  - Bernard Croft Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Clippings and Papers, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Avril M. K. and Judith Reading Correspondence, 1992-2003; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - American Carillon Music Editions (ACME) Correspondence, Catalogs, and Royalties, 2000-2016; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks, Volumes 1-2, 1968-1987 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks, Volumes 3-4, 1987-1992; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks, Volumes 5-6, 1993-1996; 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks, Volumes 7-8, 1996-1998; 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks, Volumes 9-10, 1999-2002; 9 folders (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook Materials, Programs, Articles, Certificates for Hammond, 2003-2017 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook Materials, Thank You Notes to Hammond, 2003-2007 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook Materials, Letters to J.S. Hammond, 1992-2012 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook Materials, Notes and Articles on Retirement for J. S. Hammond, 2018 (Box 10)
  - Programs and guides, 1939-2019; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Selective service papers, 1969-1970 (Box 12)
  - Certificates and service awards, 1972-2006 (Box 12)
  - Greeting cards and Guild of Carillonneurs of North America badge, 1974 and undated (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, A-B, 1982-2012 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, C-D, 1979-2020 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, E-F, 1979-2005 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, G-J, 1986-2012 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, K-L, 1984-2019 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, M, 1984-2020 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, N-R, 1977-2012 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, S, 1966-2004 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, T-W, 1981-2021 (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, W-Y and unsigned, 1979-2020 (Box 12)
  - Duke diplomas, 1968; 1996 (Box 12)
  - UNC diploma, 1971 (Box 14)
  - T.J. Anderson, Broke Baroque sheet music, 1997 (Box 14)
  - T.J. Anderson, Broke Baroque programs and notes, 1997 (Box 12)
  - Retirement book, 2012 (Box 13)
  - Rare book room photograph of Samuel Hammond and profile, 2010 and undated (Box 13)
  - Duke University Chapel calendar, 2018-2019 (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, unsigned, to family and friends, 2019-2021 (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, Duke University Libraries, 2020-2021; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, Duke University String School, 2020-2021; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, Duke Chapel, 2020-2021; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, Duke faculty, staff, and alumni, 2020-2021; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Tribute and sympathy correspondence, Guild of Carillonneurs of North America, 2020-2021 (Box 13)
  - Donations and testimonials, 2021 (Box 13)
  - Obituaries and articles about Samuel Hammond, 2021 (Box 13)
- Carillon Recordings, 1929-2007; undated
  Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - James H. Semans Funeral, 2005 Apr 26 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0001)
  - Roy Hamlin Johnson, 2007 Jul 26; 30 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0002)
  - Duke University Baccalaureate, 1999 May 15 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0003)
  - Roy Hamilton Johnson's Advent and Christmas Performances, 1998 Dec 9; 1998 Dec 21; 1999 Jan 1; 1991 Jan 4; 1991 Jan 6 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0004)
  - Roy Hamilton Johnson's Carillon Recital, 2007 Jul 19 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0005)
  - Motetus, for Carillon, 1995 May 17 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0006)
  - Roy Hamilton Johnson's Easter Service Performance, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0007)
  - New River Nocturne, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0008)
  - New River Nocturne, edited, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0009)
  - Three Pieces, Roy Hamilton Johnson, 2007 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0010)
  - Meanders, Roy Hamilton Johnson, 2007 May 18 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0011)
  - Eastertide Carillon Recital, April 6, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0012)
  - Easter Services, 2002 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0013)
  - Roy Hamilton Johnson, 2000 Mar 16 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0014)
  - Easter Services, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0015)
  - Roy Hamilton Johnson's Lent Services, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0016)
  - untitled, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0017)
    Includes works by Barnes, Handel, and Bach.
  - Bok Suite, Roy Hamilton Johnson, 1999 Jan 12 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0018)
  - Otis' Crest, undated (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0019)
    Side A: Re-recording of 6 April; Side B: 2nd half-copy of Otis' Crest.
  - Sewanne Summer Seminar, Samuel & Hammond, 1997 Jul 8 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0020)
  - Anton Brees Plays at Bok Tower, 1929; 1959; 1979 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0021)
  - Anton Brees Playing at Duke, 1949; 1965 (Box 11, Audio-cassette UA17010008-CS-0022)
    Side A: Songs played at Duke; Side B: Anton Brees Interview and recital.
  - The Carillon, Daniel Michalak, undated (Box 11, Data-cd UA17010008-OP-0001)
    Includes Carillon #1 in C Major; You Satisfy the Hungry Heart, and Taking of Exams.